[Music]
do
hello everybody greetings and welcome to
the ask a budget show i hope you're all
doing very
well uh before we begin let's see who
all is there let's see let me greet
everybody mohit justin
aniket shri hari dungar singh johan
favors
arya
and everybody else greetings great to
see you all
and
i hope you're all doing well like i said
and let's get into the questions i have
picked a bunch of questions and let's
see how many i can answer tonight
i suppose i should begin with the
question that
the people have asked the most so let me
get into that
so this is by rajat chopra the question
is why are the arab countries condemning
nupur sharma's statement on whatever
this seems like a coordinated effort
what's your take on this
issue okay so i'm going to answer the
geopolitical aspect of this i'm not
going to go into what the lady said
whether it's right whether it's wrong
i'm not getting into that
i'm going to answer the geopolitical
aspect so the entire uh
this entire scenario this entire
situation started with the
statements by qatar right
and uh most of the other arabic etc
countries followed suit
so let's understand what really is
happening here
let's talk about qatar
do we know where qatar is let me show
where qatar is in case some of you may
not know it
uh let me go to the map and show and
take a look at where qatar is so we know
where india is obviously so let's go
westwards
to the uh
arabic peninsula
and here we have this tiny nation of
qatar
all right this is where qatar is the
capital is doha
and the entire fraca so so to say
started with the statement of qatar
so let's take a look at the history and
the background of qatar just a bit to
understand what's happening
so this nation qatar used to be a
british protectorate
it was a british protectorate until 1971
right
then if you go if you go further a
couple of decades it was the launch it
was one of the launch pads
for the 1991 us invasion of iraq
it was also a launch pad for the 2003 us
invasion of iraq
qatar participated in the 2011
u.s operations in libya which deposed
the dictator muammar gaddafi
qatar is known to be funding anti-assad
anti-russia
rebel groups
rebel groups in syria now why don't you
take a look at which
which groups uh constitute the so-called
rebels fighting against putin
and and assad in syria
it's very interesting names will turn up
over there right so qatar is funding
anti-russia anti-assad rebel groups in
syria right
qatar is participating in the supposedly
saudi-led war in yemen now we know who
the saudis work for who is the puppet
master of the saudis we know who that is
i hope you all know who that is
that's what qatar is doing
qatar also facilitated afghanistan's
handover
from the u.s to the taliban and most
recently qatar has been designated by
the us as a major non-nato ally
and we know that the
the tv channel al-jazeera
operates out of qatar so essentially if
you look at this entire sequence
this entire pattern if you look at it it
becomes quite obvious that qatar is a
sock puppet of the united states
that's what qatar is
and qatar i believe was designated a
major non-nato u.s ally
right after the or right around the uh
russian
uh intervention
in ukraine
and we know the idea what the attitude
of the u.s and the west has been
vis-a-vis the indian stands on ukraine
india has
steadfastly refused to take sides in the
ukraine crisis and india is looking out
for its own national interest and that
has not gone down with the west
especially the us the west is the us
and then all of this has started so
qatar is the first nation in the in the
gulf region that issued whatever
statements it issued against india
condemning whatever right
and various other uh
gulf nations followed suit all of these
gulf nations are essentially in some way
or the other
sock puppets
of the superpower
and of course very some some very bright
and intelligent people will point out
hey abhijit
even the taliban issued a statement even
iran issued a statement these are not
puppets of the us
well there is something called fomo
f-o-m-o
fear of missing out
so that's what motivates motivated
countries like iran and regimes like the
taliban to also follow suit because we
don't want to be left out when everyone
is doing this
right
so uh the question you're asking is that
what you're saying is that this seems
like to be a coordinated effort
obviously it's a coordinated effort
the united states is really upset with
india
for taking the stance it has taken in
the ukraine crisis
the u.s wants india to bend the knee and
become a part of the of the
well
of the coalition of the willing
essentially become a vassal state of the
us india will not do that
and therefore the u.s is trying
everything in in the book in the
playbook to pressurize india
and to and to hit hit back at india in a
variety of ways it will use all the
tools at its disposal to do that
so what we are witnessing is a
continuation of that these arabic
countries
like i have mentioned multiple times and
i have demonstrated this india has
excellent relations
with these arabic countries with whether
it's the saudi saudis
whether it is oman whether it's the uae
or whatever else
india has excellent relations with them
and it's just because of external
influence that these countries
are doing what they're doing
so this is a passing phase
it doesn't mean that our relations have
gone bad with these countries it doesn't
mean that we have capitulated in front
of their superior firepower or whatever
what we are seeing is a manifestation of
a bigger power at play and that power is
way more powerful than india is as of
today
and therefore it is prudent
it is prudent to play the long game
let them get some small wins now doesn't
matter
what matters is the long-term
prosperity
of the nation and the long-term national
security and national interest that's
what matters
so uh
i know lots of people have expressed all
kinds of outrage on social media that
india has bent the knee this government
is so weak blah blah blah blah blah
that is not the case
this government is playing a long game
now you may see it whichever way you
want this is how i see it
so this is what i have to say about this
issue
right next question
this is by bruh
bruh
the question is could you give a brief
a brief on machiavelli's dualistic
strategy of a fortuna
could you give examples of events from
the century okay
fortuna and vertu is not a dualistic
strategy these are two concepts that
machiavelli nicola machiavelli uh
wrote about in his works
his for his most famous work obviously
is the prince
right the prince by nicola machiavelli
that's what makes him so famous so in
his works in his writings
he wrote about these two concepts for
tuna and verto all right what are these
two things
so fortuna is the things you can't
control see
machiavelli wrote about power he wrote
about what a ruler should do in order to
uh
to rule properly to to hang on to power
to stay in power and to maximize his
power
and to rule effectively and so on right
so
according to machiavelli there are two
main forces
in
uh
there are two main forces at work when
it comes to rule to when it comes to
power when it comes to ruling a nation
or a people or kingdom or whatever or an
empire right
the first
force at work is for tuna which is those
things that you can't control fortune
chance
let's say you are the king of a city
which is sitting on the banks of a river
right
it's a major river
and suddenly there's a huge massive
flash flood that comes
the river goes into a massive flood and
it what's going to happen it's going to
destroy the city this is something the
king cannot control
that is for tuna
what is vertu
virtu
is not being good it means the ability
to to stay in power the ability to rule
effectively and well
that is vertu so let's say you are a
king of a city that is sitting on the
banks of a river the river once in 50
years undergoes a big big spate of
flooding
the king knows this he knows that this
is something he cannot control but he
can
build dams he can build embankment mints
and he can do whatever it takes
in order to minimize the effect the
deleterious effect of the flooding so
that is what the king can do he cannot
control when the flood will happen he
cannot control the the magnitude of the
flood but he can control his actions in
in mitigating
of a possible future flood so that is
virtue where
right
so the ability
the chinese call it the mandate of
heaven
if you are in if you are in power
and if you are able to rule effectively
then you have the mandate of heaven then
the gods are smiling on you
things are there which you can't control
but whatever you can control you do it
the best
do you do it to the best of your ability
that is virtue that is the virtue of a
ruler it doesn't mean the ruler has to
be virtuous and noble and kind and
benevolent and all that
it means that the ruler should know how
to rule and how to stay in power and how
to
uh
rule effectively and hopefully do
something good for the country that may
also be part of virtue but it's or the
ability to rule well
that is virtue
so fortuna is what you can't control
where to is what you can do in to the
maximum amount of ability these are the
two things these are the two the two
forces that are in balance
when it comes to
ruling
right so that's what machiavelli wrote
about the dualistic strategy of fortuna
things you can't control and things you
can control
and the interplay of these two forces
so that's what it is events from the
century events every day are a
combination of four tuna and vertu so it
is something that does apply in in the
real world
i mean
you can you can think i mean
look at
the current events in afghanistan
there are certain things
most of it
so ask let's ask ourselves this question
the americans recently last year in
august around august they withdrew from
afghanistan
how much of this was fortuna and how
much was verto
how much of this was unforeseen
circumstances that forced them to
withdraw
and how much of this was their own
decision to withdraw
i think it was all their own decision to
withdraw i think they got tired of it
right they they decided that the time
was opportune for them to leave
afghanistan and they handed over the
country to the taliban using oman as
as an intermediary in the
process right
so that sort of thing
so
these are the two main forces at play in
the career of any ruler of any regime of
any government things they can do
and things they can't control
and the best rulers have
a great amount of vertu and they rule
well and effectively so those are the
most powerful and most
impactful
rulers and regimes
so that's a little bit above about
fortuna and verto
next question is by asbita it is said
that the portuguese discovered the sea
route to india in 14 and 98.
yes 1492 was was
columbus reaching america
and 1498 was basically going around the
cape of good hope and reaching
colic order calicut india
so they discovered the sea route to
india in 1498 there's a gap of more than
a century thereafter for the british to
reach india
as they first came to india in 1608
what
do whether the reasons for such a long
gap are known all right good question
so the portuguese first came to india in
14 and 98
and the british came more than a century
later why
why this big gap
so to understand why it took the british
so long to get their act together you
have to look at british history
so if you look at the history of england
around this time
late 1400s to the 1600s
you will see
that there's a lot of turmoil political
turmoil instability
you had the plantagenet dynasty
which was in power in the 1400s edward
the fourth from mid
from
1460s to 1480s yeah that was edward iv
then you had edward v who was there for
a few
just one year less than one year
then you had his uncle richard iii who
came to power in 1483 and he was in
power for two two and a half years
then there was this great battle the
battle of bosworth field
in which richard the third was killed
and the tudor dynasty began
henry vii right so uh and richard the
third is a very celebrated king he was
supposed to be very evil and all that
and they recently discovered his
skeleton
under a car park just uh two three four
two three years ago right very
interesting case
so
so in
1485 i believe rich henry v came to
power the first ruler of the tudor
dynasty he ruled for quite a while until
the 1500s 15 9 15 10 then henry viii
came to power now henry the eighth is
this great king you know
uh he ruled for like almost
nearly 40 years
his rule was quite tumultuous he was
very ambitious
he
he saw himself as a world conqueror or
whatever at least conqueror of europe
but he never really did anything
he had many many wives he killed many of
them you had them beheaded and all crazy
guy
but very interesting ruler
so
there was this entire period of
instability
so this begins the the edward the fourth
was the
1460s henry viii was until the 15 40s
1547 i think he died
then there was more instability his
daughter henry viii's daughter came to
power
married the first also known as bloody
mary who tried to undo everything her
father had done
she
reintroduced catholicism as the main
de facto religion
of of the country
she
[Music]
she tried to undo everything her father
did so she was in power for about five
years more instability because of that
then after her her half sister elizabeth
the first came to power in 1558 i think
and she ruled for nearly half a century
so it is when elizabeth
came to power
that things stabilized
and her age was known as the elizabethan
age the golden one of the golden ages
maybe the golden age
of england
and she reintroduced her father's
policies
protestantism and the anglican church
and all that and she was quite liberal
she was quite fond of the sciences and
progress and all those things so it is
under her rule
that uh england became a scientific
superpower and a technological
superpower
there were some these conflicts with the
spanish in which the
british the english navy was able to
defeat the spanish the spanish armada
and all that
and it's only in the
around the end
of the 16th century that things were
quite stable that england was stable and
prosperous
and i think it is in 1599 that the east
india company was formed and the first
contact
the first ship
of this company
reached india i think in 1608
surat
in western india
and the first factory was established in
surat in 1613
and a couple of years later there was
the second factory established in
southern india in machilipatnam and so
on so forth
so there's a gap of a century between
the portuguese
supposedly rediscovering india
and the british making contact with
india because of this entire period of
instability political instability
infighting and all that in england so
that is the reason why there's a such a
long gap hope that makes sense and good
question
right prashanth says can india fulfill
all its oil requirements from russia in
order to reduce dependency on the gulf
countries if yes then why isn't the
government doing so why do we trade with
countries that have agendas against us
okay
i'm sure that the russians can supply
all the oil that india needs
so india can cut off all that all its
ties with the gulf and get everything in
russia but then will it not create a
dependency on russia itself
think about that
see in any
in geopolitics in business in trade in
investing in whatever
in life
you cannot be dependent on only one
source of whatever of energy of money or
income or whatever you need to have a
balanced portfolio let's say you're an
investor
let's say you have one crew rupees to
invest
let's say you have a million dollars to
invest that you wish to wish to invest
somewhere will you invest all of that
into just the stock of one company what
if that company crashes you're gonna
lose all your money
you need to have a balanced portfolio
you need to look you need to look at the
different companies that are out there
and invest in the best performing
companies the companies that have been
performing well for a long time
those are good bets and you can have
some part of your some percentage of
investment in more speculative ventures
maybe cryptocurrency maybe nfts maybe
some
new upcoming uh startups or whatever so
you need to have balanced portfolio you
cannot put all of your eggs in one
basket you cannot put all of your money
on one horse
similarly when it comes to
energy uh supply when it comes to oil
when it comes to
yeah oil
we need to make sure that we have
multiple sources
that we rely on if we put all of our
bets on russia
and something goes wrong there we don't
want anything to go around there but
what if something goes wrong then what
will we do if we burn our bridges with
the other countries what do we do we're
gonna be in in trouble
that's why
we need to have a balanced portfolio we
need to get some oil
from the gulf from the saudis
from uma from kuwait from from iran
get some oil from venezuela
get some oil from nigeria get some oil
from russia get it from multiple sources
keep your your
your basket
balanced that's what we need to do
maybe some of these countries have
agendas against us so what
we are giving them good money
for something that is useful to us we
can trade with our enemies we trade with
china come on
china the chinese are not for india's
friends we know what they seek
we know what they seek but we trade with
them
as long as it benefits us we can engage
in such activities
right so that is why
we are not cutting off our sources over
our
uh
our trade with the gulf companies we
need their oil it's a mutually
beneficial relationship we have
cultivated a very good relationship with
various gulf countries with the saudis
with the uh umanis with the kuwaitis and
so on so forth with the parsi i been the
iranians persians
and we're going to continue that
it is in our national interest to do
that
and that's what will continue so
that's the reason and and we are
certainly importing
oil from the russians why not they are
offering us oil at good prices
at discounted rates we will certainly
take advantage of that and we have
increased the amount of oil that we are
purchasing from the russians it's all
about
your national interest it's all about
mutual interest
mutual benefits
so that's how we play the game that's
how the game is played in geopolitics
next question uh what okay earth hin
that's wrong what's wrong after atal
bihari vajpayee the economy of india was
still growing it even reached eight
point seven percent per annum
after 2012 it started to go go down slow
down in 2019 it was down to five percent
it went to minus 23 percent during covet
now it's rising again so this gentleman
or lady whoever it is is saying that
so i had made a statement somewhere
sometime somewhere that uh
after 2004 the economy kind of tanked
right
so maybe there was not a very accurate
statement but what i said is that during
the upa
era ten years the economy the policies
the economic policies were not good
enough
and the economy tanked so this gentleman
is pointing out pedantically
so
that uh for some time it was doing well
it reached eight point seven percent per
annum and only after 2012 it started to
go down so let's let's understand how
things are
in
in life
whether it is in a sport whether it is
in a business whether it is in
entrepreneurship whether it is in
running a country whether it is in in
the economy
there is always a characteristic delay
between cause
and effect
right let's say you you have a website
and you are you have been doing seo
search engine optimization but you are
not getting
the kind of results you want you are
only getting 10 000 visitors per month
then you bring in a new person for seo
and they change the strategy they tweak
things up so are you going to see
results overnight no
after they implement the new policy it
will take a certain amount of time
before the results become visible
there is a characteristic inherent delay
between cause and effect let's say you
you are the manager of a football club
your club is doing terribly
so you the manager is sacked a new
manager is brought in this new manager
implements a lot of changes he brings he
sacks a lot of non-performing players it
brings in a bunch of uncapped young
players with a lot of potential it
changes the tactics strategies
everything you think you will see
results overnight you may have another
bad season but if you keep on doing this
maybe next season you will see the
results there is always a gap
between cause and effect a
characteristic time delay
when it comes to the economy
mr vajpayee during his time he
implemented lots of reforms in the
economy
in a nation of 1.3 billion people when
you implement reforms there's gonna be a
significant amount of time before you
see results
so whatever work was done during the
vajpayee government
until 20 2004
what happened after 2004 is that the
watchpad government lost the election a
new government came in and they started
reaping the benefits of the reforms the
vajpayee government had done
and the economy started rising it
decided doing well
it's only after 2012 that the new
changes that the new government had made
became apparent i mean their their
effect became apparent and that's how
the economy started going down
in 2014 mr modi's government came to
power they started owner on a
on a program of reforms and for the
longest time nothing was visible the
economy was not doing well only now are
we seeing the results
of all the reforms that are done since
2014 now the economy is rising it's
rising it's rising i think it's going to
keep rising of course there is
volatility
globally
that also has an effect but overall the
graph is rising now there is a
significant delay between cause and
effect when you're running a massive
gigantic country of 1.3 billion people
when it comes to the reforms that you
implement
and the time for it for those results to
be visible in in the real world for the
effect on the economy to be visible
so please understand this whether it is
a sport whether it is business whether
it's running an economy there is always
a characteristic delay between cause and
effect and
the best players understand that delay
very well
so if you're a business person
if you're a sports person and if you
understand how much time it's gonna take
for something to be to become apparent
then you can do very well and if you
have no idea of how it works you will
give up before you will see results
that's how it is
okay this is a tremendously long
question allah patel says abhijit is
right mao was very clear in his mind he
did not know how but he definitely knew
what
his opponent the founder of taiwan
chiang kai-shek was also very
clear-headed
on the other side all
indian leaders of the subcontinent
gandhi nehru jinnah never had any
clarity of what they wanted to do this
lack of clarity is a signature quality
of an indian mind wow that's okay
the lack of clarity is a signature
quality of an indian mind the indian
mind can never be clear going as far as
chandragupta or ashok we see this
problem
those two guys also royally destroyed
their own empire created by chanakya
in a way clarity of mind is not an
accident it's a very rare phenomenon
among all races
as of now only the western and far
eastern countries show clarity of mind
the only hope for us is to learn from
the gita and other indian texts and get
some clarity of mind
chances are very slim
if it had to happen it would have
happened we are staring at an iron home
wall we should give up and we are doomed
okay so what allah is saying is that the
lack of clarity is a signature the lack
of clarity is a signature quality of the
indian mind
and ever since the time of chandragupta
in ashok we are seeing this pattern
chandragupta apparently destroyed his
own empire
i'm sorry
did chandragupta destroy his empire
he forged an empire out of nothing
and ashok expanded that empire
so that's not quite consistent with
reality but okay
and after then after that time there has
been no clarity of mind in any indian
ruler or whatever
so um
what was the kushan empire which
stretched all the way to the caspian and
the aral seas some will say
kaneshka was not indian okay
even if that is obviously absolutely not
true but even if that is the case what
about the gupta empire which again
conquered
all the way to balik
bulk
and and beyond most likely and the whole
whole of the indian subcontinent
uh
samadhi gupta for instance did he not
possess clarity of mind
samudra gupta
if you look at his career
his entire career
from start to finish was an extended
military campaign
no clarity of mind i think he had
singular clarity of mind
the same goes for kumaraku the same goes
for
for skanda gupta and so
the great kashmiri
conqueror the great kashmiri king he
conquered most of india he also
conquered central asia did he not have
clarity of mind my dear friends
what about the great chola emperors
raja raja chola and rajendra
rajendra chola conquered the entirety of
southeast asia was there no clarity of
mind there
he conquered
all the way to the philippines
you still find inscriptions in sanskrit
in the philippines
was there no clarity of mind what about
the the great marathas what about the
great shivaji the great chatrapati
maharaja did he not have clarity of mind
please let us
see it's like this
all general statements are false
you see the inherent contradiction in
what i just said
i said all general statements are false
and that itself is a general statement
so i totally disagree with the
assessment
here that
the lack of clarity is a signature
quality of an indian mind
that is not the case
and this is this this sort of perception
of this sort of
this belief
is the consequence of the last 1000
years of humiliation
india has
gone through it is still undergoing
it is still passing through the
millennium of humiliation
in which you had defeat after defeat you
had a lot of resistance you had
victories as well you had the maratha
empire which defeated the invaders and
so on but again we fell prey to the next
invader the
the europeans the british and so on so
we have gone through a millennium of
humiliation
and because of that and especially
because of the education system which
teaches us that we are all losers that's
why we people
get get this
sense or this feeling or this this
belief
that
indians are losers our people are are
not great
the lack of the significant quality of
an indian mind is a lack of clarity and
so on that's not the case
even today we have
certain leaders who have a singular
clarity of mind and purpose
and like i said some time ago
there's always a certain delay between
cause and effect
so
be patient my friends
whoa this is a big big big thing let's
let's take a look this is by muhammad
ahmad muhammad ahmad greetings from
pakistan
you defeated us you defeated us four
times since independence
every time you guys declared a ceasefire
without capturing any territory of ours
you might even defeat us fifth and even
sixth time you guys might defeat us
defeat us a hundred times
you guys are not undefeatable
we can afford to lose a hundred battles
we will certainly be attacking you or
not in first time as well
you cannot afford to lose a single
battle
you have to win every battle but we want
just one victory to capture your
territory and obviously to genocide you
i am a teacher in rawalpindi
i teach this predator philosophy to my
students have a good day
so this is what uh
mr muhammad ahmad has to say
he teaches this predator philosophy to
his students so i would like to say to
mr ahmed thank you so much
for sharing this with us you have you
thank you for your honesty
so this is what india is up against
india we can say if all we want
about us being the same people
hamara
we have the same dna all of us yeah it's
true
it's true indians and pakistanis have
the same dna indians and the pashtuns
have the same dna we are the same people
we have the same ancestors and yet
this is the attitude in pakistan this is
what they teach them
and it's true
that we have fought for wars since 1947
each of those wars was initiated by
pakistan
india responded india did not fire the
first shots ever
india defeated pakistan every single
time right
and it was india that declared a
ceasefire every time without capturing
any significant territory yes india
liberated bangladesh in 1971 but india
did not reincorporate bangladesh into
india
india allowed bangladesh to become a
separate nation
so once again india did not capture any
territory
and whatever little territory was
captured here and there was given over
by the politicians after the ceasefire
and like mr ahmad is saying we can
defeat them 100 times but we are never
going to do to them what they want to do
to us
so all it will take for them
is to defeat india once
so that is something
this is a rare moment of honesty so i
would like to really uh thank
mr ahmed for for sharing this with us
and this is what they are made to teach
and maybe maybe they agree with it this
is what their students are taught over
there in pakistan
so understand this my friends and i'm
sure the indian government knows this
this is a different kind of government
it's not like the previous regimes we
know
that pakistan is a threat that's not
going to go away unless we uh deal with
it in the appropriate manner
so uh yeah that's what it is so there's
no question here it's just a statement
it's something that he he wanted to
share with us
so yeah thank you so much for sharing
that and you are right
that is indeed the case
okay vishal mahajan says will ireland
unite following the left-wing shin
feigns victory in the recent elections
in northern ireland
will this increase the demand for
scottish and welsh nationalism as well
interesting question so what's happened
is that uh the shinfan
has become the largest party
in the uh northern ireland assembly
right so what does that mean so what is
the the story
so shin fein is
the party that was um
fighting for islands northern ireland's
independence from uh
from the british from britain see
northern ireland is under british
occupation
it is actually british occupied ireland
it's not northern ireland it is british
occupied let's let's take a look at the
map yeah
the map always helps when we deal with
these things so
here we are
and if you look at the the map here
this here
is the i island of ireland and it is
politically cut into two portions the
largest portion is
main island or just ireland
and in the north you have northern
ireland so northern ireland is under
british military occupation the people
of ireland wish to be free from britain
okay
so it is under illegal or so to say
illegitimate british military occupation
and the history is bloody
the british have
violated all kinds of human rights in
northern ireland
they have acted like a terrorist force
and that is that is what it is so uh
there was this resistance going on in
northern ireland for decades the shin
fein was involved in it the ira irish
republican army which has at least two
factions was involved in that and and so
on
right and this this went on for decades
so there was this entire uh
um
never-ending
cycle of violence
uh that went on the violence spilled
over into
england as well
right there were bombings by the ira in
england uh the prime minister of britain
margaret thatcher once narrowly escaped
with her life when her hotel room was
bombed
with
a mortar or something
and she narrowly escaped with her life
because she was in in a different room
at the time
so this is something that went on for
decades right uh now
so then what happened
so somehow magically all these troubles
they went away in 1998 somehow magically
it's very strange so it's like this
in 1997
tony blair became the president
of uh
great britain so so called great britain
right
now tony blair
was he has been accused rightly or
wrongly
of being a u.s lap dog okay
he was a british he was a u.s lap dog
that's what people say and there may be
some some justification to that
allegation
the moment this guy tony blair comes to
power
in england
the troubles in ireland end magically
yeah
and the northern ireland assembly
was established one year later in 1998
and then there were elections in
northern ireland and it became a
functioning democracy and all was well
and the shin fein renounced violence and
blah blah blah blah blah as soon as a
u.s puppet comes to power in
in britain
and before tony blair came to power the
uk was not quite so amenable
to u.s demands about its foreign policy
and that's why and somehow
coincidentally
there was a lot of trouble in ireland
for decades but as soon as a proper lap
dog comes to power all the troubles end
i'm just
pointing out this strange coincidence
i'm not i'm not asking you to put two
and two together okay
so
so the shin fein renounced violence the
troubles ended after tony blair came to
power just magic just magic happened
overnight right and the assembly was
established in 1998 and this year i
think it was in may that the latest
election was held so-called election
so in the may 2022 election in the
northern ireland assembly the shin fein
became the largest political party they
got the most seats they are the
party with the most seats now they
do not
so this is the
the thing is this
the northern ireland assembly doesn't
really have any real power
northern ireland is still under british
military occupation
the northern ireland assembly parliament
whatever you want to call it
is
it's something like the elections the
british used to hold in india before
the so-called provincial elections and
all that that was just a joke a sham it
was not democracy
when you are under foreign occupation
and that foreign occupation power holds
election in your country those elections
are illegitimate they are null and void
that is not democracy
in a real democracy
your country needs to be free from from
foreign interference
and your own
institutions like your own election
commission without any external
interference should whole elections that
is
real democracy and that's a legitimate
election
so the northern ireland assembly
elections are illegitimate and
democratic they are a sham
designed to fool the world into thinking
that everything is well in ireland
all right
so uh the shin feins victory means
nothing the shin fein for whatever
reason in 1997 98 they suddenly
magically decided to renounce violence
and to renounce the the demand for
for independence so to say so they're
coming to power means nothing
means absolutely nothing right it will
not increase any demand for scottish or
wealth welsh nationalism nothing of the
sort
the entire
uk
it it doesn't have an independent
foreign policy or independent internal
policy it is
one of the small elements of the
overall u.s empire it is a vassal state
it does whatever it's told
and of course you have elections and
also it all looks like things are well
and there is democracy not democracy
actually is one of the biggest shams or
scams that has been pulled upon the
world
in in very few places do you have
genuine democracy yeah without any
foreign interference
so uh to
to conclude
this uh so-called election in northern
ireland and the so-called
victory of the shinfan means absolutely
nothing it's going to do nothing ireland
will remain under
british occupation and britain
essentially is under u.s occupation
whether you
realize it or not so that's just how it
is this is the uh
anglo-sphere which is all
uh
more or less controlled from one
location in north north america
washington washington dc that's what it
is
okay samiksha goyal says in rock edict
13 ashoka himself said that he has
converted to buddhism how can you say
that there is no evidence of it you are
wrong
okay samiksha says that so let's see
what is the truth
did ashok himself said that he had
converted to buddhism let us take a look
at what the rock edict 13
has to say about this let me share in my
screen
inscriptions of ashoka
here we are
so this is
the translation of the inscriptions of
ashok this is the 12th rock edict we
will we need to go to the 13th one where
is the 13th rock edit okay this is the
sanskrit or other uh devanagari
transcription translator
dev
version of what is written there i think
it was written in pali which is an upper
branch language of sanskrit a descendant
language of scripture so let's go
this is what the inscription looks like
this is the
transliteration of all of that into the
latin script which you think is the
english script
and here is that
the translation okay let's let's take a
look at what it says
it begins when king devanama priya
predation had been anointed eight years
the country of the kalingas was
conquered by him
one hundred and fifty thousand in number
where the men who were deported then one
hundred thousand in number were those
who were slain there and many times as
many
those who died
after that now that kalinga has been
taken the king
is devoted to a zealous zealous study of
morality to the love of morality
and to the instruction of people in
morality okay great there is this is the
repentance of the ivana priya on account
of his conquest of the country of the
kalingas
for this is considered very painful and
deplorable by devana priya that while
one is conquering an unconquered country
slaughter death and deportation of
people
are taking place there
but the following is considered even
more deplorable than this by the king
and so on and so forth obedience to blah
blah blah blah blah lots of stuff very
nice pr on behalf of ashok
if there is misfortune to friends
acquaintances companions blah blah blah
this is shared by all men it is men is
considered deplorable by that by devanam
priya there is no country where these
two classes the brahmanas and the
sramanas do not exist except among the
yonahs or the yavanas or the greeks
and there is no place in any country
where men are not indeed attached to
some sect or some class or whatever
therefore even the 100th part or the
thousandth part of those people
who were slain who died and were
deported at the time
of the when the country was taken would
be considered very deplorable by the
king okay he's a great man full of
morality
desires towards being self-control
impartiality kindness
and this conquest has been won
repeatedly by devanam priya here among
all his borders even as far as the
distance of 600 yojanas
where the yonah king named yoga or
antiochus
is ruling
and beyond this antiochus there are four
kings who are ruling there is the king
named
is ptolemy ptolemy of egypt yes
named ante kina named makkah named
alexander and so on from the south the
chola and the pandas are ruling as far
as tamraparni or sri lanka
likewise in the king's territory among
the yonas and the kambojas nabakas
bhojas etc etc etc people are conforming
to devanama priya's instruction in
morality how strong a king he was so
righteous so moral that everybody is
conforming to his morality
even those to whom envoys go do not go
having heard of the duties of morality
and so on so forth are conforming very
good conforming good this conquest has
been won by this everywhere causes the
feeling of satisfaction good
firm becomes the satisfaction and blah
blah blah this satisfaction is of no
consequence the king thinks only the
fruits of the other world are of great
value and so on and so on and so on and
so on so forth and that is where the
edict ends where does it say he has
conquered he is converted to buddhism
please please tell me where does it say
that the great king ashok has converted
to buddhism i just showed you the entire
rock edict the entire text
look it up yourself it's available in
the public domain
i have not
dragged it out of some secret location
this is something you can google and
find for yourself do some homework and
do some research of your own
so please tell me where does it say that
the great king ashok
converted to buddhism
nowhere in rock edict 13 or any other
rock edict does it say
that the king ashok converted to
buddhism please
check
your facts right
there you are next question
global affairs says
this is a very large question
one request to all of the viewers if you
would like me to answer something it is
best if you keep your questions short
one or two sentences
i i see some people ask very interesting
questions but they write a whole wall of
text
so that's not gonna work please keep
your questions short anyhow let's take
this
the kalinga empire has been a glorious
empire in itself okay
apart from being one of the pioneers in
maritime in maritime business they made
india's oldest systematic dance form odc
the lord jagannath temple was one of one
of the first etc etc etc etc etc
can you please explain about the
policies of the kalinga empire and the
objectives of the rulers
and how did the ancient roman historian
plainly mention this
region of india as oritiz in his book
called natural history in 7780
he says this region as where and when
there are there be no shadows
okay
kalinga look kalinga is one of the major
major
forces major engines that drove ancient
india
kalinga obviously is now what we call
orisa it's on the eastern coast of india
in case some of you don't know where
orisa is i hope there's nobody like that
but let me just share my screen
and show where
odisha
is
let's get out of the british islands get
come back to india
and here
on the east coast of india you have
kalinga
which is now called odisha and the
northern part of odisha is called utkal
which is uttarakhalinga
so you have bhuvaneshwar you have puri
you have the city of
cuttack
if i can find it somewhere
yeah here it is
and then so on so forth
wonderful place wonderful people
beautiful culture great history and so
on so forth right
that is kalinga so kalinga was one of
the great
engines
cultural
economic
military maritime etc engines that drove
ancient india
kalinga is
the region
or the empire
that
spread indian culture eastwards
for the first time
as far as we know
so
this this dates back to at least two and
a half or three thousand years before
today so kalinga the people of kalinga
used to trade with southeast asia
with uh neighboring
kingdoms
across the bay of bengal like burma
thailand
indonesia
southeast asia funan
in cambodia and vietnam and so on so
forth right
so they are the the people of kalinga
are the ones who first enculturated
southeast asia with indian culture
expose southeast asia to indian culture
right
and
even today in southeast asia in
indonesia especially i believe that
indian people are still called kalingas
right so that tells you how how old this
connection is
so kalinga definitely has a great
history great rich culture beautiful
culture beautiful
geography
great people all of that
so that's what i can tell you about
kalinga and uh
yeah i don't know what pliny wrote about
kalinga
he called it oritiz we don't know what
it is maybe orisha maybe not we don't
know about that but great history it is
certainly something that people should
study about read about
because it's an integral part of the
greatness of ancient india
right nanda gopan says why are almost
all international cricket grounds in
australia
located in the coastal region even
though it's a very large country or
continent very good question
let's take a look
at okay so it's like this uh
there is something called the pareto
principle
the 80 20 principle so that kind of
applies to australia
so so all of the cricket grounds in
australia where is australia okay let's
take a look at australia on the map
how do i get the map in here one second
where's the map
here is the map this is australia so the
major cricket grounds in australia are
in brisbane
in sydney
in
melbourne
adelaide
hobart in tasmania
and all the way
east
in perth
and there's also one in darwin i believe
some cairns there's one in cairns
and one in darwin as well but those are
not really major cricket grounds the
major ones are the gaba
in brisbane
the scg in sydney the mcg melbourne
adelaide oval
and the bel revolt in tasmania and the
waca are the new ground in perth right
now why is it so so let's take a look at
a different image
let's take a look at the population
distribution
of australia shall we
what's the population distribution of
australia like so this is the population
distribution of australia
the brighter parts are where you have
the highest concentrations of population
in the country and that is precisely
where they have the major cricket
grounds
as you can see in the eastern part
there is the the region of perth where
you have a high concentration of
population
and the interior of the country
is all empty it's dry it's parched it's
inhospitable and nobody wants to live in
that place because it's really hot
really really really hot
it's the coastal regions that have a
nice temperate cool climate so that's
where the major population centers are
and that's where
your cricket grounds are located
so it's very simple the cricket grounds
are located where you have the major
concentrations of population
and why do you have major concentration
of population there because those are
the nicest places to live in in
australia
good climate and good access to all the
resources and obviously far away from
the
dry interior of australia so that's the
simple reason why it is so
chinmay says why are jupiter and saturn
called gas giants are they made of gas
does it mean if hypothetically a human
sets foot on one of these planets there
will be no solid surface to step upon
good question so jupiter and saturn are
called gas giants because yes they are
made up of gas
both of the planets
both of these planets are roughly
hydrogen and roughly 10 helium there's a
very small amount of other trace
elements and all that but that's very
minor
most of it is
hydrogen
and 10 helium so if you look at jupiter
for instance its mass is about 320 times
the mass of the earth
okay it's a massive planet 320 times the
mass of the earth roughly approximately
give or take something
and
as you go further inside the planet
so it's all gas so there is no actual
surface if a human being were to
hypothetically
set foot on the planet
you would just sink all the way all the
way down all the way down to the core
or until a region where your
your body's density
becomes less than the density of the
hydrogen because as you go deeper into
jupiter the
atmospheric pressure becomes
greater and greater eventually the gas
becomes liquefied
and very very very hot so i think the
surface of jupiter is defined as the
as the region where
the the the atmospheric pressure is
equal to the
equal to the atmospheric pressure of the
earth that is
defined arbitrarily as the surface of
the planet but it has no actual solid
surface it has a solid core most likely
maybe it's made up of metallic hydrogen
which is a weird form phase of hydrogen
which may be surrounded by molecular
hydrogen maybe it has a rocky core maybe
it has a carbonyl for a score
if there is carbon at the core of
jupiter it will be compressed so much
that it will become diamond so maybe
there is a massive amount of diamond at
the core of jupiter and same goes for
saturn in the case of saturn
the mass of saturn is roughly
100 times that of earth maybe 90 times
95 something like that
and
so this the internal structure is
similar
in some ways to jupiter in in the case
of jupiter the core temperature of the
planet is about 35 000 degrees celsius
in the case of saturn it's about 10 000
degrees celsius so that's the kind of
temperature you have so that is the
reason why these two planets are called
gas giants they are giant planets and
they are made up of gas mostly hydrogen
some helium right so that is the reason
why
uh someone someone says
can we see planets of other stars
telescopes
well if you have a telescope of your own
and if you try to look at a star you
will not see planets
you can't so not through your typical
amateur or backyard astronomy telescopes
but you can nowadays
use a specialized instrument called a
corona graph
and you can attach it to the major
telescopes in the major uh observatories
on our planet play observatories like
the wendelstein observatory in germany
or the hill telus telescope at the
palomar observatory in california and
the us
or the european southern observatory vls
very large telescope in chile and so on
so forth these are massive telescopes
and you can attach this instrument
called a coronagraph
to these telescopes in a technique
called direct imaging and what it does
is that it obscures the
the surface of the star
and if you obscure the the star itself
then you can suddenly see what's around
the star
in that case you are actually able to
observe
planets visually through telescopes
uh using this technique so let's take a
look at
some images if i can find some
of
corona uh chronograph images of
exoplanets let's go to google our good
friend google
okay coronagraph
corona graph
exoplanet images
let's take a look at this
what does it throw up
so this here
could be that
yeah in this case as you can see the
the
the disc of the star is obscured and you
can see some some of these uh
exoplanets around that this is a gif
image
and if you look here the arrow it
demonstrates the movement of an
exoplanet around a star
so this is a direct image this this
technique is called direct imaging
imaging and you can actually
see
exoplanets this again here shows
an image of an exoplanet and so on
so yes nowadays it is possible and as
this technology gets better you may be
able to see better and better images of
fans through this technique
so yes in some cases we can actually see
exoplanets through the telescope
okay ankit kumar says the country which
has dominance in the indian ocean has
dominance over the world
what should the indian navy
and the indian government do
to make this strategic location fall in
their favor
how
andaman and nicobar's military strategy
is making india unbeatable
can you please explain this
okay uh let's go back to the map where
is the map
right let's take a look at the andaman
nicobar islands
and the indonesian region
okay
so this here is india and south of india
is the indonesian region as you can see
india
has this incredibly
central
geographical position in the indian
ocean region it's a god gifted
position it dominates the entire indian
ocean region
now why do people say that the country
that dominates the indonesian region
will dominate the world it's because
the majority of the world's trade
takes place in this region so it uh
there are multiple troop points in this
region the first choke point is soas
the suez canal region
so as you can see this is the city the
the egyptian city of soviets also ways
and there is this canal
so which connects the mediterranean sea
to the red sea so that is a major choke
point
the second choke point is the strait of
baba al-mandib which is right here
between djibouti and yemen the gulf of
aden
then you have the strait of
hormuz
which connects the persian gulf to the
gulf of oman that is another choke point
then you have certain dog points that
people may not be aware of which pass
through the luxury islands and the
andaman
islands and then you have the two major
choke points here which is the strait of
malacca this narrow region
and the sunda strait
over here
is it called the sunda strait it's
called something else whatever it is
it's a narrow choke point over here
and all of these choke points are easily
accessible to india so if india has a
powerful navy and a powerful air force
india can close off shut down these
choke points at will
and that's why india has such a huge
opportunity to become a major
geopolitical player i'm not saying india
should blackmail the world or anything
india should be a responsible
geopolitical power and india always has
been that
but
it is something that you can india can
use to make china behave
if china indulges in any misadventure in
the in the tibet
india border then india can make china
behave by its actions in the indian
ocean region
because the majority of china's
imports and exports
go through
all of these stroke points
and india can with its navy and its air
force control this so that is why it is
said that the country that dominates the
indonesian region will certainly
dominate the world
and what should the indian navy indian
navy and indian government do about this
india needs to invest in a better navy
uh in in a more massive navy we need a
lot more ships we need a lot more
submarines
india needs to stop investing in
aircraft carriers which are nice to see
we don't need that we need submarines
aircraft carriers were the capital ship
of the 20th century the submarine is the
capital ship of the 21st century it's
virtually undetectable it is invisible
these are stealthy deadly silent killers
that's what india needs to invest in
conventional submarines and nuclear
submarines
and india should invest in a
in a coast guard which is more powerful
you can call it the navy or whatever and
we already have these unsinkable
aircraft carriers the andaman islands
the nicobar islands and the electoral
violence
so we don't really need to invest in
these massive ships that cost billions
of dollars we should invest in
submarines and lots of submarines
because quantity has a quality of its
own so these are the things that indians
do the second question is that
how do the
how andaman and nicobar's military
strategy is making india unbeatable
so these days i'm getting this question
over the past couple of weeks but
apparently india has this unbeatable
strategy in the andaman nicobar islands
and india is killing china or whatever i
don't know where this comes from
but
wherever you're getting these ideas from
it is not consistent with reality
which strategy in the andaman islands is
making india unbeatable what india
should do
and undermine indicobar islands is to
militarize them
india should
create
multiple
airstrips air force bases india should
invest in multiple ports in these
regions in in these islands
in submarine bases in naval bases india
should create a2ad
bubbles anti-access area denial bubbles
by putting by installing
batteries of cruise missiles
anti-aircraft missiles all that if india
does that
then it will make india virtually
unbeatable india is not doing that
so i don't know what strategy people are
talking about these are i don't know
where these ideas come from that there
is some strategy that is making india
unbeatable in the andaman islands india
is virtually doing nothing
there is
i think one or two airstrips or air
force stations maybe one maybe two at
most
in this region
i think it's known to everyone campbell
bay
so that's what it is and beyond that
there is very little there may be five
or six or maybe 10 sukhoi fighters
sitting there at any given point in time
if if we are lucky maybe one or two uh
poseidon poseidon anti-submarine warfare
airplanes
and maybe a couple of indian navy ships
and that's all
there are no submarine bases there's not
much of
development that's happened there so
there is no strategy that
as such
so any claim that anyone is making that
there is some incredibly unbeatable
strategy in this region that india is
using to beat china or defeat china or
kill china
that is wishful thinking it is not
consistent with reality
i
see india is in a good position visa
china
china were to start a war with india
we can deal with it properly
we can defeat them
we can defeat them in a defensive war
and we can make them suffer significant
losses but india is not in a position to
start a war against china
so we are still
if we compare the two militaries and
economies we are still significantly
inferior to the chinese but we have
certain advantages that the chinese
don't have and they will not mess with
us because of those region reasons but
there is nothing happening
in the andaman nicobar islands that can
be considered to be an unbeatable or
whatever strategy so so that is
certainly not the case
right next question
sujata says namaskar my question is when
the u.s can keep an eye on indian
nuclear tests with their satellites why
can't we keep an eye on terrorist
factories present in pakistan with our
satellites
and expose them to the world and
pressurize pakistan to give permission
to india
to the indian army to eliminate
terrorists okay
the americans have maybe hundreds
of military satellites or spy satellites
right
in in orbit
these are deployed all around the world
india
also has a number of satellites that are
classified as
remote sensing satellites
etc
which essentially are satellites with
specialized instruments
which
view the earth which which look at the
earth
the surface of the earth
in a variety of frequencies and
wavelengths
these satellites have very good
resolutions maybe a meter maybe a foot
maybe a centimeter
yeah
and they may because of various
wavelengths and all they may be able to
peer through clouds
they may be even able to see what's
happening on the ground in darkness at
night possibly
right we don't quite know
what all is going on there but we have
india has a number
of satellites
what the exact number is let's not go
into that
and these satellites keep an eye on
india's surroundings
whether it is the west in pakistan
whether it is in pakistan kashmir or
wherever else whether it is in tibet
whether it's in the indian ocean region
wherever we have the
assets
in place
to keep an eye on everything that's
happening so we are certainly
keeping and keeping an eye on the
terrorist factories present in pakistan
with our satellites
these satellites you can call them
remote sensing satellites or military
satellites or spy satellites same thing
now
let's say we are looking we are seeing
what's happening in pakistan terrorist
factories what is the point of exposing
it to the world
yeah here we are here we go we have the
proof what's the point the world knows
what pakistan is doing the world has
known for decades what pakistan is doing
how many times we expose them to the
world
it makes no difference the world doesn't
care
the world doesn't care they know what
pakistan has been doing they they know
that the pakistanis have been bleeding
india since the 1980s in kashmir and
other places the question is
real question is who is funding all that
who was funding pakistani terrorism in
india who was financing pakistani
terrorism in india
that is the real question and because it
is the u.s that was doing it that's why
the world will always turn a blind eye
to pakistani activities so exposing the
pakistanis is going to solve no problem
whatsoever they will just ignore it the
western media will never run such a
story they know what's happening
now about pressurizing pakistan so that
they will give permission to the indian
army to eliminate terrorists
the indian army needs permission not
from pakistan but from the prime
minister of india
that is the only permission the indian
army needs
when the indian army gets a go ahead
from the prime minister of india they
don't go and knock on pakistan's door
do you remember balakot
do you remember the surgical strikes did
the indian army go and knock and take
permission no
so when the time is right the right
things will be done we don't need
anybody's permission we know what the
pakistani
army is up to
we know where the terrorist factories
are everything is known when the time is
right the right action will be taken
there's no question of taking permission
or exposing anyone there's no need to
expose anything
there's no need to take any permission
all that needs to be done is to act when
they
appropriate when the moment is opportune
when will the time be right that is for
the indian government to calculate based
on the global geopolitical scenario
aman singh says what should be the pro
most prominent personality traits of a
renowned military leader
look um
personality doesn't matter
there have been military leaders who
have been extremely cheerful and
boisterous and social there have been
military leaders who have been very
reserved introverted
aloof
so the personality doesn't matter but
what is the most important
characteristic
or trait
of a military leader
the most important characteristic of a
military leader
is that they should succeed
that's all succeed
and when i say a military leader should
succeed i don't mean that they should
win every single battle no no no no no
no no
you can fail
in the short term
take the great
mongol conqueror sri chingish khan
for instance as an example
his main characteristic is that he did
not
lose
a single military campaign after he
became the great khan of the mongols he
did not he won every single military
campaign
but his army lost a few battles here and
there in those military campaigns a
military campaign is like a world cup
a world cup
when your cricket team or your football
team goes to the world cup they're gonna
play a number of matches a number of
games
it doesn't matter if you lose one or two
games here and there what matters is
that you win the final match you reach
there you have to first qualify for the
quarter finals you make make sure you do
that then you qualify to the semi-finals
then the final and then you win the
final before that in the group phase
it's okay to lose one or two games as
long as you can qualify for the next
round so a military campaign is like a
world cup it is okay to win to lose one
or two small battles here and there you
can make a couple of chess sacrifices if
you want but overall you have to win the
world cup so a military campaign is like
a world cup the great sri chingas khan
the great the kind the beneful and the
wise
leader chung is khan he did not ever
lose a single military campaign
so the most important
characteristics
characteristic of a military leader is
they should win
they should succeed
that's what that's what matters
so that is what i can offer to you in
brief
okay so miksha goyal says i think ethics
are very important and we will never be
able to condemn pakistan for terrorism
if we ourselves join hands with a
terrorist organization
supporting the taliban means you are
going against humanity
you know
i don't remember who it was that said
this i think it was the great
rajendra chula i think who said this
he said
that if you are a king
and you do everything
and you do whatever it takes
to ensure the long-term
prosperity and success of your empire
then you can never go to heaven you will
go to hell because you will have to do
things
that other people will see as morally
unjust or morally or or immoral
as a ruler
the highest morality for a ruler the
great vishnu said this
the highest morality for a ruler
is to ensure the long-term
security and prosperity of the country
of the nation of the kingdom and its
people that's all
and you have to do whatever it takes
to ensure this
you may have to indulge in
assassinations of political leaders you
may have to wage wars with foreign
countries
you may have to
join hands with foreign terrorist
organizations to destroy your enemies
you have to do whatever it takes to
ensure the long-term security and
prosperity of your country of your
nation of your kingdom and its people
your duty is to your people and your
people only not to everybody else
you may have to be immoral for that you
may have to be unethical for that and
you may have to go to hell after you die
for that but that is a sacrifice you
should be willing to willing to take
willing to make
and if you cannot do this you are not
worthy of being a king
that's how it goes ethics and morality
are fine
for the common man and woman
for a king it's a different ballgame
altogether so these wonderful words
you know they're nice in books and all
that but the real world is a real world
right so that's how it goes that's how
the game is always played
and uh whether you agree with it or not
well
who are we to criticize what
what uh vishnu gupta said he is the man
and he's right
okay this is
the next question
okay this is by titraklitos
i can read the greek alphabet because
in physics we have
greek greek symbols
right so
says namaskaram there is a theory that
says that ancient indians probably
sanskrit or tamil
probably whatever
explorers of the so-called indianized
kingdoms of the malay archipelago
and other southeast asian islands
reached the pacific coast of south
america by crossing the pacific ocean
and are considered as the ancestors of
the olmecs
what are your views about this
let's go to the
map once again
where's the map here's the map on the
map on the map
okay
this is the map
so
the theory like uh tetra klito says is
that
ancient
indians according to this theory or
whatever hypothesis may have crossed the
pacific ocean
and reached uh
southern america south america what is
said here
reach the pacific coast of south america
by crossing the pacific ocean
and maybe the ancestors of the olmecs
okay so as you can see the pacific ocean
is vast it's vast
it's a it's a big huge massive expanse
of water
we do know that about 5000 years before
today ancient indians did make it to
australia
right and the only way to reach
australia is by sea so indians could do
that they had the ability to cross the
ocean reach australia maybe they did it
through from indonesia maybe from
kalinga maybe from southern india
but they had to cross the ocean to go to
australia we know it because there is
unmistakable genetic evidence of indian
genetics in the australian
aboriginal populations and this
introgression happens around 5000 years
before today when the saraswati from the
phase of our civilization was at its
peak
so if the indians could do that 5000
years ago it is certainly possible it is
certainly within the realm of
possibility that some indians may have
crossed the pacific ocean and reached
the pacific coast of south america it is
possible
now the olmecs
the olmec civilization
let's go back to the map sorry the olmec
civilization was found in
eastern mexico
on the eastern coast on the atlantic
coast of mexico which is not quite far
from the western coast from the pacific
coast
and some uh artifacts of the almex were
also found on the western coast of
mexico as well
and the olympic civilization dates back
to about 3000 years before today
right and if you look at the artifacts
the the massive stone carvings etc that
you that the almex left behind
they uh let's let's uh see what that
looks like shall we let me go back
to
google
once again let me share that
olmec
carvings
i'll make carvings or make statues or
whatever so these are the colossal heads
that the olmecs uh left behind
and if you look at the facial features
of all of these people that are depicted
in these massive stone carvings
they look like people who are of african
origin i mean that's the kind of facial
features that you see
mostly as you can see these facial
features don't resemble indians
these facial features resemble people of
african
origin or ethnicity i mean that's the
stereotypical look that you find in
africa among among certain african
peoples right not in india
not
the average indian person doesn't look
like this right
so from the circumstantial evidence that
we have over here
it would appear that if
somebody crossed over
crossed an ocean and reached this region
it may have been people from africa
now we don't have as far as i know uh
a skeletal evidence from the olmec
civilization if you we can
find that then they could maybe do some
dna estimating and figure out what sort
of uh
haplogroups etc are present among the
population so
as of today
we don't have sufficient data points and
sufficient evidence
to either prove or disprove a theory of
indian origin but from the
circumstantial evidence that we have it
looks like it's not indian it looks like
it's probably some
african origin ethnic group possibly
possibly
so my views are that we still don't have
sufficient data therefore we cannot
really come to any conclusions but from
whatever little evidence we have it
looks like it may be from africa not
from india
but time will tell
okay mark douglas says if chavda is
right in the west is just an american
hegemony
responsible for all the bad in the world
i know it's there okay whatever
responsible for whatever ask yourself
why does all mass migration always
happen from the east to the west
i am not seeing millions of displaced
syrians fleeing to russia they all come
to the eu
i am not seeing millions of displaced
europeans fleeing to india either the
flow of people is definitely from india
not to india and therefore chavda is
wrong
brilliant impeccable logic by mark
douglas
see
so what i have said is this
that the term superpower is a euphemism
for empire
the united states exhibits all the
classical characteristics of an empire
of an imperial power
and you know what the characteristics
are from the study of in of human
history 10 000 years of human history
going back to the persians to the the
acadians to the romans
to the various indian empires the
chinese mongols and so on so forth right
there are certain characteristics that
an empire has and the us has that the
u.s is essentially a continuation
of the british empire the anglo-saxon
saxon empire i'm not saying the u.s is
responsible for all everything that's
bad in the world they have maintained a
certain kind of order which and which is
predicated on their hegemony and their
writ
but
that's just how it is i'm not saying the
us is responsible for everything that's
bad in the world some people try to
misconstrue that
in that form it's not quite the case but
and the point the mark douglas is making
is that all mass migration
always happens from the east to the west
and therefore i must be wrong but the us
is an empire
really
when we are talking about mass
migrations about about people migrating
from point a to point b in search of a
better life
they don't care whether they're going to
an empire or not
all that matters is that they will have
a better life better living standards
if you look at india
in 1947 india had a life expectancy of
28 years or 30 years
india's gdp per capita was was in the
pits
everything of value had been stolen
plundered from india by the british
the west has been had been enriched at
the expense of india
india was a hell hole that's what the
british made of india
and therefore indians were desperate to
escape this hellhole especially after
the
the regimes that ensued after 1947 you
know the british puppet regimes
i mean not quite the british populations
but
various prime ministers etc who did not
do anything to ameliorate the indian
economy and make lives better for india
for the people of india for for decades
and therefore indians wanted to
e-migrate immigrate out of india
and if you look at the west the per
capita gdp in the west is like at that
time was more than 50 times out of india
massively better living standards and so
who cares if it's an empire or whatever
you can get a better life there by by
moving there
and then becoming a citizen there so
that's what everybody wanted
even today
let's go back to thousand years the
roman empire was a was a hegemonic power
cruel power
they indulged in
massive genocides all across europe see
what they did to the helvetian peoples
see what they do
to the celtic peoples see the the read
about the military campaigns of julius
caesar
see what they did in carthage
wide-scale genocide
and yet all the roads led to rome
everybody wanted to go and live in rome
because you had the highest and best
living standards there
as long as you became a citizen of the
roman empire you were treated well
so that's how it goes
so this argument is not quite
uh grounded in logic i'm afraid to say
right
rama lakshmi says
you have said that the decline in u.s
imperialism over the world
and their influence is dropping my
question is if such a superpower is in
decline in what way does it get affected
year decades later
is it in standards of living or economy
or military or only the influence over
the nations what sectors would be
affected if any
when any power goes into decline
everything declines
the economy declines
the rule of law internally in the
country in the country declines its
influence globally
declines its geopolitical influence
declines its military
reach declines its industries crumble
you can see that over and over again in
history
if you look at the western roman empire
how they declined
they were the greatest power in the
world
at least in europe in the western
hemisphere for quite a long time and
then what happened italy went into like
the dark ages
right
what happened to the byzantine empire
they also were a massive empire and then
they slowly shrank shrank shrank and
then eventually it was just just like a
city-state around constantinople
the same thing you can see in various
other empires it's a gradual process
that takes centuries sometimes usually
decades
30 40 50 years
it's a slow process of decline and decay
i don't wish that on anybody
but it's it's a cyclic process the world
the the history of the world shows that
empires rise and fall rise and fall rise
and fall in cycles
okay
so uh
if a superpower or an empire is in
decline there is
all sectors are affected
sometimes you may have a civil war if
you look at the
dynastic cycles in china which are
imperial cycles
usually when an empire or a dynasty
crumbles there's a period of extended
civil war that's what chinese history
shows us again and again and again
so that is from the example of china
in other places like
uh rome etc you all
also had
episodic events like civil wars and
strife and all that
industries would go for a toss and so on
so it's never
an orderly process it's often very messy
and that typically when when you have an
empire at a global scale it goes into
decline it's going to create a lot of
chaos
and a lot of instability in the world
and that is never good for anybody so
one hopes that
things go go well and
but let's see let's see how it goes you
know we cannot stop the
tides of history and things will
proceed in a certain way
okay pallak chudasama says my 11 year
old daughter nitya
has been asking this question for weeks
now how do blind people dream or can
they dream
and my seven-year-old son mrig asked a
strange question what is the life cycle
of air
you know kids
ask the most interesting questions kids
still have
an active imagination and a curiosity
and and
thirst for knowledge and after they go
they spend a few years in the education
system all of that is smashed out of
their heads so i'm glad that kids are
asking such interesting questions
so let me take the second question first
which is asked by mrig
what is the life cycle of air see
air
is a gas
the air that we breathe that we live in
is
part of the atmosphere of the earth
right
the atmosphere of the earth is
technically or or it is it is uh
by
convention uh
said to extend a hundred kilometers
above the earth's surface and beyond
that you have space
so that's just the convention
so the air we are breathing is part of
the atmosphere of the earth it is a gas
more about 70 i believe nitrogen 28 or
so oxygen the rest is carbon dioxide and
so on and so forth right
so it is simply
gas molecules
it is not a living
creature
or or a living being it's not made of
living organisms and since it is not a
living thing it doesn't have a life
cycle
right
so if you look at the history of the
earth
over the past three and a half four
billion years or whatever how long
however long it has been since the earth
formed in the primordial solar system
the atmosphere of the earth has
undergone major changes
and significant uh compositional changes
so that happens over millions hundreds
of millions and billions of years
in the beginning
the earth's atmosphere was very very
different
uh
much of it was what was it i'm not i
don't quite remember what was the
composition but there was very little
oxygen
and there was a
and then then what happened was there
was this this bacteria
that that
that were living in the oceans
and they gave off a lot of oxygen which
caused the mass extinction event
that there is the great oxygenation
catastrophe they call it that happened
about three four billion years ago you
can look it up how
when it happened
and then oxygen became the pre one of
the major components of the atmosphere
and it is something that is
indispensable for us without it we will
die
so it's something that has changed a lot
over time but it doesn't actually have a
life cycle because it is not a living
thing right the other question is how do
blind people dream
or can they dream yes of course they
will dream now it depends some people
most people who are blind
are people who became blind because of
some illness or some accident or
something which means that in the past
they could see they once had the
they once had sight or vision and then
they lost it
so for such people they still have the
memory of
of seeing things and such people even
though they cannot see with their eyes
when they sleep they would still dream
things that they can see
but a small percentage of people who are
blind are born blind and they have never
seen anything in their life for such
people i would imagine that the the
dreams would be through the other senses
auditory senses or whatever so they may
dream things
without the experience of any kind of
vision so that's a very interesting
question so so most blind people who
dream would still still have visions in
their dreams even though
they their eyes don't function but a
small percentage who are born blind
would not would dream
in the form of sounds and other
experiences
that's how it would typically be
okay let's uh
take one or two more questions lecture
says i
as a 16 year old my parents
keep asking me what career and degree i
want to pursue they are also asking me
what at what
what which university i want to join
here in australia
i absolutely hate the prison that is
cool as i walk to school i'm cursing
under my breath i want to be an
entrepreneur
how do i find a business mentor and
learn skills i'm mainly looking for
guidance please help
okay you're 16 years old you want to be
an entrepreneur you hate school i get it
school is a pain
and you forced to study stuff that
doesn't really have any real relevance
in in the real world and so on yeah
but uh
so you're still very young you have a
long way to go
i would offer a word of caution firstly
entrepreneurship
looks like a very glamorous thing you
make money you live the fast life and
you succeed and all that
but
the truth is that very few entrepreneurs
actually succeed
it's a long process of many years it's a
long grind
the success stories you see are never
overnight success there's a whole period
of
of grind that that lies behind that
all overnight success takes five 10 15
years
right and most entrepreneurs and most
businesses fail or there are multiple
failures before you have a success
and
that's how it is so and and the life of
an entrepreneur is often very very
harsh very painful very brutal
very agonizing
and that's that's what is never shown in
the media and movies and all that
so that is something you have to keep in
mind
secondly you may want to be an
entrepreneur but do you have the skills
the aptitude for that of course you can
develop skills for sure so how do you do
that
so i would say that you know what
you should still go to school you should
still go to college you should get a
degree as as as a backup plan and in the
meanwhile what you can do is you can
attend business conferences or whatever
in your free time
meet other
entrepreneurs who are doing stuff
try something on your own with some
small amount of money
yeah
read as many business books as you can
it's not easy you have to put in the
hard work
give yourself two years and and try to
read a hundred business books
go to amazon go into the category of
books for business look at all the five
star reviews or
four star plus reviews
take the top hundred books and try to
read all of these hundred books in the
next two years go to business
conferences go and mingle with
entrepreneurs and try to gain some kind
of
wisdom from them talk to them ask them
about what they do how what was the
journey like what is that process like
right
and that's how you make connections and
if you're lucky you may even find a
mentor or two and
so that's that's the process you go
through it's a long process you're still
16 you have a long way to go i certainly
wish you all the best but i would
offer a word of caution that you should
still go through school go through
college get whatever degree you need to
do you need to get
whatever is best for you based on your
personal aptitude and strengths
and always have a backup plan don't put
all of your
eggs in one basket don't put all your
money on just one horse always have plan
b plan c
so that's what i can say
all the best sir
okay one last question
ashwa thomas says what is the difference
between reading a book or listening to
listening to an audiobook which do you
prefer i prefer to
read physical books
i i read really fast my reading my
reading speed is very very high
uh
it's something i've developed over the
years and decades i read a lot
so i prefer reading
because when someone talks this they
talk at a certain speed my mind it kind
of it's frustrating i i read so much
faster than somebody can speak i kind of
speak also fast because of that perhaps
so i prefer reading books but there is a
certain value that audiobooks have even
for me
so for instance if you go for a run
let's say you want to go for a run in
the morning half an hour one hour
whatever run for an hour
when you're running
as long as it's not in the in traffic if
it's on a treadmill or whatever you can
listen to an audiobook at the same time
so that is a good experience that's a
nice experience you're running you you
it's exhilarating and you're also
listening to an audiobook so that is a
good way of q of of
of listening to an audiobook also if
you're in the gym exercising working out
you can
put an audio book on in the background
so or if you're cooking i enjoy cooking
at times so if you're cooking and you
have this time you're spending the
kitchen
you can keep an audiobook or a podcast
or something on and
keep it going in the background so that
that helps
so that's how i use audiobooks but
typically i prefer to read physical
books
all right let's take a few questions
from the live chat if you all have more
questions you want to ask me now is your
time to shine my friends go for
it is learning math a skill yes learning
math is a skill
there
to anything there are two components for
tuna
and where to so
not like that but
if you have the aptitude
of doing something let's say you are a
you are a gifted runner
right or you're a gifted swimmer so you
have the ability to swim well or to run
well but if you don't practice if you
don't put in the hard yards if you don't
spend the hours perfecting your craft
then even though you are talented you
will not reach your full potential
similarly
if you have the aptitude for math but
you don't practice if you don't put in
the hours and hours and hours you will
not good become good at it so yes
learning math is a skill
and more than talent hard work is what
matters in anything so yes
learning math is a skill
um
yeah i don't remember kumara but it was
an interesting story
um
what's the history of satya pratha
please watch uh the conversation i had
with dr meenakshi jain on this channel
in which we go into detail about the
history of satya pratha and the myths
and fabrications that have been
constructed around this
so-called supposed practice please watch
my my my
interaction with dr minaxijn on this
channel and you will get everything you
would like to know about this particular
matter
um
okay what else do we have
my views on toscan files any relation
between the former prime minister indira
gandhi and the kgb that are two these
are two different questions if you want
to talk about the task and files the uh
lal badu shastrikes etc please watch my
interaction with anujar on this channel
podcast number podcast number one
i think it was in january this year
on this channel so
if you want to know about that go and
watch that podcast you will get to know
whatever you need
okay where else are we
um
what are the possibilities of
indo-pacific dominance of india in the
next 10 years zero
we need to dominate the indian ocean not
the indo-pacific pacific is too far that
will come
in the future if it does
what's your view on the bharat series
book by jay said i haven't read it sorry
maybe i will someday and then i'll talk
about it
does india have too much democracy like
the chinese say yes india has too much
democracy
too much of democracy why it is this too
much democracy
right where are we
i found something and it disappeared
okay
uh
was sri lanka part of ancient india as
gandhara
sri lanka was definitely part of indian
civilization the
sri lankan people their ethnicity is
indian
let's say you are in london england and
you see a person walking down the street
who is of sri lankan origin what is the
first thing that comes to your mind this
person is indian
right
so the sri lankan ethnicity is the
indian ethnicity we have the same
genetics same dna same origins
everything
and culturally also the sinhalese and
tamils are indians their culture is
indian so yes it was just as much part
of india
civilizationally as gandhar
see
today we think about nations
nation-states
that is a very new concept the
nation-state concept is a very new
concept it's been around for a fraction
of of an instant in the context big
picture of human history
historically we had civilizations
nations and empires india was always a
civilization
india is a civilization state and
gandhar
used to be part of indian civilization
and sri lanka you can say is still part
of the civilizational fabric of india
even though it's not part of the nation
state of india
so
yeah that's what it is
what qualities should i develop to
become an ifs officer ifs means indian
foreign service you want to become a
diplomat
to be a diplomat
you should be very much in touch with
current affairs
you need to understand the history of
the world very well especially the
history of the last 100 years
starting from the 20th century onwards
so the turn of the century whatever
happened the first world war the second
world war the cold war
you need to understand the cause and
effect sequence the cause and effect
chain the causality change the dynamics
you need to understand geopolitics you
need to understand economics
um
it would help if you
learn multiple languages also you know
at least one foreign language we all
speak this foreign language whole
english but one more one additional
foreign language
things of that
i don't know what uh exam you have to
pass i think it's the same exam and then
they select people from for the ifs ips
ifs etc whatever
uh so i'm not quite sure what the
mechanics and dynamics of the selection
procedure are but from my perspective if
you want to be a diplomat you should
know all of this and eventually you'll
be assigned to some nation perhaps and
you would want to learn or study more
about the nation its history and its
political
uh
political structure and all that yeah
so that is what you need to do to be a
good ifs officer a good diplomat
all right let's see one or two more
questions
what's your view on dark matter with
reference to vedic serum video i have
not watched
the
the said video so i don't know
uh dark matter as we know is one of the
major
unknown
components of the universe
the universe is about 70 dark energy
about 25 roughly roughly roughly
roughly 69 70 percent dark energy
roughly 25 24 25 dark matter and roughly
or so
visible matter
what is dark matter that's what we are
trying to figure out what is dark energy
we don't have the least idea
but at least dark matter we have some
some some clues
it's something that interacts
only gravitationally the weak
interaction seems to well there's no
evidence for it so
mostly
most likely it's only gravitationally
interacting maybe it is uh
super heavy dark matter shdm
cold dark matter
and there are a
number of candidates that have been
proposed and so on so this video that
you are referring to unfortunately i
have not seen it but this is what i can
say in very brief about
about dark matter
right um
let's take maybe one question
let us say
why did ancient southeast asians adopt
indian culture other than rather than
chinese culture because indian culture
was way more influential in india as a
civilization was way more influential
and far-reaching than the chinese
civilization and culture indians were
enterprising india was a
major
maritime
culture and civilization indians went
everywhere by boat and by ship mainly by
ship
that's how indians reached all over
southeast asia
and indian culture was not supremacist
exclusivist and predatory it actually
contributed something valuable and
positive to southeast asia it was never
imposed upon these people by force and
that's why they were so impressed by
indian culture that they adopted it for
themselves and today you have
various local
examples local manifestations of indian
culture all across southeast asia
and that is now their native culture
so it's because of india's enormously
influential nature
that this happened the chinese statesman
and diplomat hoshi said
that ancient india conquered china
without ever sending a single soldier
across the himalayas
we conquered china culturally and the
chinese greedily lapped up indian
culture and absorbed it deep into their
civilization today they claim that
buddhism is a chinese thing
well
for many for
all intents and purposes buddhism you
could say is something that has chinese
characteristics today
so they are trying to claim indian
culture and civilization for their own
well that's how it is
all right let's um shall we take one
more question or are we done
i can see lots of questions here but
um
okay last question is has india crossed
the lacs claimed by the chinese foreign
minister that they found indian weapons
i think this claim was made during the
galvan clashes and the media or the
social media is trying to regurgitate
this today it is something from 2020
it's a claim they had made in 2020 after
the galwan clash in order to justify
their
misadventure that old news report from
for 2020 is now being republicized today
in 2021 and now everyone thinks this is
what they've claimed today no it's an
old claim
anyhow
that
we don't quite recognize the lse
or we do recognize it to some extent but
like they say
in diplomatic balance
that both sides have differing
perceptions of the
line of actual control
so there is no
accepted boundary it's some
rough thing that nobody quite
agrees upon and therefore these claims
are made from time to time we don't have
to take them very seriously
all right ladies gentlemen
thank you very much for the questions
very interesting session as always
the questions are very always very
interesting so please keep it coming
next week
let's let's do two sessions how about
that right
so until then
thank you very much for your questions
thank you
for your viewership and i will see you
next week
thank you take care